<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>🛡️Cybersecurity on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://flecart.github.io/tags/%EF%B8%8Fcybersecurity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 🛡️Cybersecurity on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</url>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://flecart.github.io/tags/%EF%B8%8Fcybersecurity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Notions of Security</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/theoretical-notions-of-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/theoretical-notions-of-security/</guid>
      <description>CIAA principles of security We have already outlined these principles in Sicurezza delle reti and talked about the concepts of authentication and integrity. Here we try to deepen these concepts and delve a little bit more on the attack vectors These are acronyms, usually called CIA and AAA for infrastructure
Confidentiality This is one concerns about the secrecy of the sent message. We do not want others to be able to access and read what we are doing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sicurezza delle reti</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/sicurezza-delle-reti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/sicurezza-delle-reti/</guid>
      <description>Obiettivi della sicurezza (!!!) 🟩 Vogliamo creare delle reti che abbiamo certe garanzie di sicurezza, soprattutto:
Confidenzialità, non vorremmo che il nostro messaggio sia intercettabile e leggibili da persone intermedie Integrità: non vogliamo che messaggi possano essere cambiati senza intervento del sender Autenticazione: vorremmo sapere con chi stiamo parlando, e vorremmo essere sicuri che non stiano mentendo sull’identità. Sicurezza operativa(Availability): vorremmo essere in grado di poter continuare a fornire il servizio (quindi non sia possibile dossare, o installare malware che modifichino il comportamento del servizio).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TLS-SSL protocol</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/tls-ssl-protocol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/tls-ssl-protocol/</guid>
      <description>First time we talked about this was in Sicurezza delle reti#Protocollo SSL But that was a simple toy model.
Secure Socket Layer Secure socket Layer and TLS add security (see security principles in Theoretical Notions of Security) on the transport layers, whereas IPSec protocol adds it to the network level. So this works on a higher level of abstraction following the ISO OSI framework Architettura e livelli 1, 2#Livelli ISO/OSI.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OTP and Stream Ciphers</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/otp-and-stream-ciphers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/otp-and-stream-ciphers/</guid>
      <description>XOR operation È una operazione binaria abbastanza semplice però ci sarà importante per andare ad analizzare dei cifrari di un certo genere. Come il ONE TIME PAD che faremo fra poco in OTP and Stream Ciphers.
Teorema cifratura con XOR Prendiamo $X$ una variabile aleatoria in $\left\{ 0,1 \right\}^{n}$ uniforme, sia $Y$ una variabile aleatoria su uno stesso dominio come vogliamo. Tali per cui $X, Y$ siano indipendenti Allora avremo che $C = X \oplus Y$ è una variabile aleatoria uniforme.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wireless attack vectors</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/wireless-attack-vectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/wireless-attack-vectors/</guid>
      <description>In this note we will talk about some common ways to attack wireless based devices.
Attacking an automated door Usually these doors are opened by radio frequency keys, and can be opened easily (e.g. replay attacks, Jam the frequency)
Jamming This is the easiest way to attack. Just send many signals to make a certain frequency un-usable in our space. But with Frequency hopping this attack is solved. See Tecnologia Wireless#Frequency Hopping But this method could be easily known and observed (enables eavesdropping, against confidentiality, a principle in Theoretical Notions of Security#CIAA principles of security.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric Cryptography</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/asymmetric-cryptography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/asymmetric-cryptography/</guid>
      <description>Public Key Encryption We now define a formally what is a public key encryption
Formal definition of Public Key Encryption We define a 3-tuple formed as follows: $(G, E, D)$ where
$G$ is the generator for the private and public keys, from now on identified as $(pk, sk)$ (public key and secret key) $E(pk, m)$ the encryption algorithm, that takes the $pk$ and the message in input $D(sk, c)$ the decryption algorithm, that takes the $sk$ and the ciphertext in input.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Block Ciphers</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/block-ciphers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/block-ciphers/</guid>
      <description>Utilizzano blocchi per cifra invece che stream generators. $n$ bits in input and $m$ bits in output generally a key is expanded into multiple keys, one for each rounds, and applied to a round function that iterates on the $m$.
DES 56 bit 3DES 56*3 bit di chiave AES che può andare a 128, 196 o 256 Solitamente i stream ciphers studiati in OTP and Stream Ciphers sono più veloci. Cipher Speed MB/sec RC4 126 Salsa20 643 Sosemanuk 727 AES 13 3DES 109 Data Encryption Standard - 1974 da IBM su commissione di NSA (Horst Feistel designed Lucifer at IBM in early 1970) - 1976 DES is federal standard with key-len 56 bits and block-len 64 bits.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sicurezza OS</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/sicurezza-os/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/sicurezza-os/</guid>
      <description>Possiamo classificare tre aree generali quando si parla di sicurezza informatica:
Hardware Software human-ware. Non tratteremo in particolare esattamente come ogni campo viene declinato, però possiamo
Una altra tendenza generale è che più è complessa più è insicura. e questo senso di insicurezza cresce in modo maggiore rispetto al lineare.
Security principles Open Design perché così può essere scrutata da più persone Economy of mechanism spiegata sotto. Fail-safe defaults questo molto importante perché molti sistemi hanno dei default che possono essere exploitati.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Key Exchange protocols</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/key-exchange-protocols/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/key-exchange-protocols/</guid>
      <description>Metodi di key exchange
Trusted Key parties (sono come Certificate authorities studiati in Sicurezza delle reti) Merkle Puzzles DH protocol Trusted Third parties Squared Key problem Un problema abbastanza ovvio è che per storare le chiavi di tutti c&amp;rsquo;è una necessità $O(n^{2})$ on $O(n)$ users Se c&amp;rsquo;è un trusted key parties il numero delle chiavi si riduce di molto, ritorna ad essere lineare!
Protocols Toy Exchange protocol🟩 TTP = Trusted Third party (simile a quanto poi si avrà in Asymmetric Cryptography) Questa è la base del servizio di Kerberos!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IPSec protocol</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/ipsec-protocol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/ipsec-protocol/</guid>
      <description>Questo è un protocollo di sicurezza a livello Rete e non più a livello socket!
Perché vorremmo avere sicurezza a questo livello? È una cosa troppo comune da dover mettere a livello superiore (ma solitamente viene messa a questo livello per la sicurezza, quindi non è implementata ovunque per dire), quindi IPsec vuole facilitare l&amp;rsquo;implementazione dei principi CIA a un livello più basso, in modo che sia flessibile e customizzabile.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical Cyphers</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/classical-cyphers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/classical-cyphers/</guid>
      <description>Introduzione a Crittografia al corso di crittografia di Christof Paar su Youtube, con aggiunte del corso Unibo.
Classifications and definitions Classification nowadays as many many applications like, and it’s a increasing important field
Cryptology (2) 🟩 La branca comunemente riferita come crittografia è divisa principalmente in due campi crittografia e cryptanalysis in cui una cerca di creare nuovi metodi per cifrare i messaggi, e l’altro prova ad attaccare questi messaggi ritrovando il messaggio originale.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory Corruption</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/memory-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/memory-corruption/</guid>
      <description>First of all, we need to have a strong understanding of how a program allocates memory during its execution. See Memoria, Memoria virtuale and other notes about Nomi e Scope, Gestione della memoria. The thing you have to remember is that
Every new function call allocates a new block, with his local variables. How the calling parameters are stored in the stack How the heap is allocated (common heap algos are in Gestione della memoria) How the stack grows (and how it can overflow it, and overwriting important data).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tor protocol</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/the-tor-protocol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/the-tor-protocol/</guid>
      <description>Some notes Mix-based systems🟨 Created in 1981 by David Chaum. Very similar to the previous one, in practice, in the end, it acts as a proxy but not only does it take and receive, but it also mixes together the packets it has received from the sources, applying its key.
Disadvantage: The public-private mixing system is very slow. For this reason, a network of nodes is established, each having a symmetric key, making it much faster.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
