<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Decentralized-Finance on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://flecart.github.io/tags/decentralized-finance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Decentralized-Finance on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</url>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.143.1</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://flecart.github.io/tags/decentralized-finance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Decentralized Finance</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/introduction-to-decentralized-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/introduction-to-decentralized-finance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;financial-markets&#34;&gt;Financial Markets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;uses-of-financial-markets&#34;&gt;Uses of Financial Markets&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section, we answer the question of what financial markets are for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raising capital&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Equity and Dept: Equity is ownership in a company, while debt is a loan. (there is also a mezzanine).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Price discovery: The process of determining the price of an asset in the marketplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Liquidity: pooling people together to have an ease of access to these assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risk management: Managing the risk of the assets.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risks could be: inflation (uncertainty on the value of the money), interest rate (uncertainty on the value of the money), credit risk (uncertainty on the value of the money), market risk (uncertainty on the value of the money), etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This allows hedging risks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have a role in economic growth (this is economic theory, we won&amp;rsquo;t delve into this).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-shareholders-of-the-market&#34;&gt;The Shareholders of the market&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investors&lt;/strong&gt;: People that provide capital to governments and companies in exchange of bonds or stocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intermediaries&lt;/strong&gt;: organizations that facilitate these kinds of exchanges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market data providers&lt;/strong&gt;: we can see these as intermediaries that sell data about markets (they usually sell licenses, for example Bloomberg does this).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Issuers&lt;/strong&gt;: organizations that sell financial assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regulators&lt;/strong&gt;: ensure the market is fair and is working properly (usually government agencies that create the rules).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, it is quite difficult to get into the market, from a regulatory point of view.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;collateral-and-over-collateralization&#34;&gt;Collateral and Over-Collateralization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collateral&lt;/strong&gt; refers to assets or property that a borrower pledges to a lender as security for a loan. If the borrower fails to repay, the lender has the right to seize or sell the collateral to recover the outstanding debt.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
