<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>📓Big-Data on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://flecart.github.io/tags/big-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 📓Big-Data on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</url>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://flecart.github.io/tags/big-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Big Data</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/introduction-to-big-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/introduction-to-big-data/</guid>
      <description>Small History of Information systems Evaluating an Information system 20k Ishango Bone is one of the first. 250 BC there was a library of Alexandria. With physical books it was very difficult to get some higher level trends. Now we can just analyze hundreds, and millions of documents in a very fast manner.
Velocity For the velocity we care about the capacity, throughput and latency. Capacity is how much you can store, throughput is how fast can you read, and latency is how much you have to wait until the first byte of data.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normalizzazione dei database</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/normalizzazione-dei-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/normalizzazione-dei-database/</guid>
      <description>Introduzione alla normalizzazione Perché si normalizza? 🟩 Cercare di aumentare la qualità del nostro database, perché praticamente andiamo a risolvere delle anomalie possibili al nostro interno, e questo aiuta per la qualità.
Tipologie di anomalie (!) (4) 🟨+ Ridondanze, non vorrei avere la stessa informazione espressa più volte in troppi punti. Update non consistente, quando per aggiornare un singolo valore devo aggiornare moltissime altre tuple dipendenti da essa. Deletion non consistente, la presenza di certe entità è strettamente dipendente da presenza di altri, nell&amp;rsquo;esempio in questione sulle slides, se elimino tutti gli utenti, elimino anche i progetti su cui hanno partecipato, mentre invece dovrebbero essere separati.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structured Query Language</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/structured-query-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/structured-query-language/</guid>
      <description>Little bits of history It was invented in 1970 in Almaden (San Jose) by IBM (Don Chamberlin, Raymond Boyce worked on this) for the first relational database, called system R. Then for copyright issues it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been called SEQUEL, so they branded it as SQL.
SQL is a declarative language With declaratives language there is a separation between what I call the intentionality and the actual process. In declarative languages we just say what we want the result to be, and don&amp;rsquo;t care what the actual implementation is like.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
