<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>📓Big-Data on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://flecart.github.io/tags/big-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 📓Big-Data on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</url>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://flecart.github.io/tags/big-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Uniform Resource Identifier</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/uniform-resource-identifier/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/uniform-resource-identifier/</guid>
      <description>URI Sono stata LA vera invenzione di Berners Lee accennati in Storia del web. Il problema è avere un modo per identificare una risorsa in modo univoco sull’internet.
Introduzione La risorsa 🟩 Una risorsa è qualunque struttura che sia oggetto di scambio tra applicazioni all’interno del World Wide Web.
Ora una risorsa può essere qualunque cosa, non solamente solo un file! Quindi è agnostico rispetto a contenuto oppure metodo di memorizzazione del dato, appare anche in questo ambiente importante vedere quanto siano importanti standard che permettano una comunicazione</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normalizzazione dei database</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/normalizzazione-dei-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/normalizzazione-dei-database/</guid>
      <description>Introduzione alla normalizzazione Perché si normalizza? 🟩 Cercare di aumentare la qualità del nostro database, perché praticamente andiamo a risolvere delle anomalie possibili al nostro interno, e questo aiuta per la qualità.
Tipologie di anomalie (!) (4) 🟨++ Ridondanze, non vorrei avere la stessa informazione espressa più volte in troppi punti. Update non consistente, quando per aggiornare un singolo valore devo aggiornare moltissime altre tuple dipendenti da essa. Deletion non consistente, la presenza di certe entità è strettamente dipendente da presenza di altri, nell&amp;rsquo;esempio in questione sulle slides, se elimino tutti gli utenti, elimino anche i progetti su cui hanno partecipato, mentre invece dovrebbero essere separati.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structured Query Language</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/structured-query-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/structured-query-language/</guid>
      <description>Little bits of history It was invented in 1970 in Almaden (San Jose) by IBM (Don Chamberlin, Raymond Boyce worked on this) for the first relational database, called system R. Then for copyright issues it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been called SEQUEL, so they branded it as SQL.
SQL is a declarative language With declaratives language there is a separation between what I call the intentionality and the actual process. In declarative languages we just say what we want the result to be, and don&amp;rsquo;t care what the actual implementation is like.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HTTP e REST</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/http-e-rest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/http-e-rest/</guid>
      <description>HTTP is the acronym for HyperText Transfer Protocol.
Caratteristiche principali (3) 🟨 &amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/images/notes/image/universita/ex-notion/HTTP e REST/Untitled.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;image/universita/ex-notion/HTTP e REST/Untitled&amp;quot;&amp;gt; Comunicazioni fra client e server, e quanto sono comunicate le cose si chiude la connessione e ci sono politiche di caching molto bone (tipo con i proxy) Generico: perché è un protocollo utilizzato per caricare moltissime tipologie di risorse! Stateless, ossia non vengono mantenute informazioni su scambi vecchi, in un certo modo ne abbiamo parlato in Sicurezza delle reti quando abbiamo parlato di firewall stateless.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed file systems</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/distributed-file-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/distributed-file-systems/</guid>
      <description>We want to know how to handle systems that have a large number of data. In previous lesson we have discovered how to quickly access and make Scalable systems with huge dimensions, see Cloud Storage. Object storage could store billions of files, we want to handle millions of petabyte files.
Desiderata of distributed file systems In this case we have a Filesystem. In 2004 google created his own FS. With hundreds or thousands of machines the systems are practically guaranteed to fail.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Storage</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/cloud-storage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/cloud-storage/</guid>
      <description>Paradigms of data storage ETL framework 🟩 This is the classical database approach: We load the data in the database and let the underlying system handle it. We won&amp;rsquo;t talk much about this but this is the general concept!
Data Lakes 🟩 We just store the data in the filesystem and we just see them as files. This is very good when we just need to read the data. Called also in situ because we don&amp;rsquo;t have a step where we have to extract the data.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Big Data</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/introduction-to-big-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/introduction-to-big-data/</guid>
      <description>Data Science is similar to physics: it attemps to create theories of realities based on some formalism that another science brings. For physics it was mathematics, for data science it is computer science. Data has grown expeditiously in these last years and has reached a distance that in metres is the distance to Jupiter. The galaxy is in the order of magnitude of 400 Yottametres, which has $3 \cdot 8$ zeros following after it.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
