<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Theoretical-Computer-Science on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://flecart.github.io/tags/theoretical-computer-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Theoretical-Computer-Science on X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>X. Angelo Huang&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</url>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/images/papermod-cover.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://flecart.github.io/tags/theoretical-computer-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Complexity Hierarchies</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/complexity-hierarchies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/complexity-hierarchies/</guid>
      <description>Intractable problems are solvable in principle, but in reality they require so much time or space that there no physical computers that can solve them in reasonable time. We would like to define a clear hierarchy of these set of problems.
Space Hierarchies Def: Space constructible We say that a function $f: \mathbb{N} \to \mathbb{N}$ such that $f(n) \geq O(\log n)$ is space constructible if there exists a function from $1^{n} \to \langle f(n) \rangle$ is $O(f(n))$ space complexity.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>La macchina di Turing</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/la-macchina-di-turing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/la-macchina-di-turing/</guid>
      <description>Introduzione Note filosofiche (non impo) Bisogna in primo momento cercare di definire cosa è la computazione e cosa è un computer. Aristotele faceva la distinzione fra proprietà essenziali e accidentali. Quelle essenziali sono proprie dell&amp;rsquo;oggetto.
Una sedia può essere fatta di legno o di metallo, ma questa proprietà è accidentale, ovvero, essa rimane una sedia indipendentemente dal materiale di cui è fatta.
Solitamente in matematica si prova ad astrarre (vedi Astrazione sul controllo per nota generale sull&amp;rsquo;astrazione).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cook-Levin and Savitch</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/cook-levin-and-savitch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/cook-levin-and-savitch/</guid>
      <description>Cook Levin theorem is important because says that in 1971 if $SAT \in P$ then $NP = P$. We will start with this idea to define the concept of NP-completeness. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the basics.
Poly-reduction Def: poly-reduction🟩 We say that two languages $L$ and $L&#39;$ defines over alphabet $\Sigma$. We say that $L´$ is poly (mapping)-reducible in $L$, $L&#39; \leq_{p} L$ when a $TM$ that computes polynomial time a function $f: \Sigma^{*} \to \Sigma^{*}$ such that $$ x \in L&#39; \iff f(x) \in L $$ This is very similar to the Halting Theorem and Reducibility#Mapping reducibility.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Halting Theorem and Reducibility</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/halting-theorem-and-reducibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/halting-theorem-and-reducibility/</guid>
      <description>Halting theorem Questo è un problema fondamentale, che abbiamo trattato anche in Fondamenti teorica#Halting problem, ma qui lo ritrattiamo, perché così lo rifacciamo per bene. In parte è stato trattato anche al corso di Logica.
Enunciato Halting theorem🟩 Questo è molto simile a quanto presente sul (Sipser 2012). Ossia consideriamo il linguaggio $$ HALT = \left\{ \langle x, y \rangle \in \Sigma^{*} \times \Sigma^{*}: x = code(M),M \text{ si ferma su } x\right\} $$ Dimostrazione Halting theorem🟩 La parte del sì è facile perché basta eseguirlo e vedere che si ferma (quindi abbiamo una La macchina di Turing#La macchina di Turing universale.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estensioni di Turing e altre macchine</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/estensioni-di-turing-e-altre-macchine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/estensioni-di-turing-e-altre-macchine/</guid>
      <description>Sono variazioni possibili equivalenti: • Nastri addizionali • Testine addizionali • Nastri infiniti su entrambi i lati • Non-determinismo • Scelta probabilistica • Scelta quantistica Si può dire che la definizione di TM è stata robusta nella storia perché tantissimi formalismi che intuitivamente sembrano essere molto diversi rispetto alla TM alla fine possono essere dimostrate essere equivalenti.
Turing con nastri addizionali Questo è presente in modo abbastanza facile sul Sipser.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time and Space Complexity</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/time-and-space-complexity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/time-and-space-complexity/</guid>
      <description>In this note we explore a theme of time and space complexity. Those are cardinal themes in Theoretical CS. Time -&amp;gt; execution step bounds on algorithms Space -&amp;gt; the cells visited by a Turing Machine when executed.
Introduction to Time Complexity This note will build upon know techniques of algorithms analysis explained in Notazione Asintotica. We will need big-$O$ notation and $o$ notation. L&amp;rsquo;idea è che il problema di decisione è decidibile se limito la lunghezza del teorema.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teorema di Rice</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/teorema-di-rice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/teorema-di-rice/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to the Rice Theorem Ci sono molti teoremi che non possono essere decisi, vedere Halting Theorem and Reducibility. Qui andiamo a chiederci quale sia l&amp;rsquo;insieme dei problemi decidibili.
Proprietà dei linguaggi TM🟩 Data una macchina $\mathcal{M}$ definiamo il suo linguaggio come $$ L_{\mathcal{M}} = \left\{ x \in \Sigma^{*}: \mathcal{M} \text{ accetta } x \right\} $$ Allora con questa definizione di linguaggio possiamo dire che una proprietà, ossia una funzione da tutti i $TM$ possibili a $\left\{ 0, 1 \right\}$ tale per cui se il linguaggio riconosciuto è lo stesso, ossia $$ L_{\mathcal{M}} = L_{\mathcal{M}&#39;} \implies P(\mathcal{M}) = P(\mathcal{M}&#39;) $$ Definiamo questa non triviale se esiste una macchina per cui è 0, e una per cui è 1 (ossia non è costante).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Turing Machines</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/probabilistic-turing-machines/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/probabilistic-turing-machines/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to the probabilistic Turing Machine Most of real phenomena are better comprehended by a probabilistic view. This pushes to build a formal model that takes probability into account
Def: Probabilistic TM Take a non deterministic TM La macchina di Turing. At each step there is a fair coin-flip that has two legal branches. So the probability of a certain branch is $$ \mathbb{P}(b) = 2^{-k} $$ Where $k$ is the length of the branch.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common problems in Theoretical CS</title>
      <link>https://flecart.github.io/notes/common-problems-in-theoretical-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://flecart.github.io/notes/common-problems-in-theoretical-cs/</guid>
      <description>This note is useful to gather in a single place the description of some common problems in CS and their theoretical implications explained in other notes.
The Clique problem Description of the problem This problem is in NP, find all sub-graphs where all nodes are connected (this set of nodes forms a complete graph).
We can prove that the problem is in NP because there is an easy non-deterministic algorithm that computes it.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
